all right
[Music]
DEET has been considered the most
effective mosquito repellent
unquestionably read this editorial in
the Journal of Family Practice it should
be the only mosquito repel recommended
by physicians with no other repellent
coming close given the dramatic efficacy
it's hard to concede that any other
repellent would ever beat it however
there are some rare reports of severe
reactions to deed not to mention the
fact that it can melt Plastics like
eyeglass frames and cell phone
components and made consumers find the
odor and sensation on the skin
unpleasant enter
picaridin overall Studies have shown a
little difference between DEET and
picardin implied at the same dosage with
some evidence pointing to a superior
persistence for picaridin all without
the irreducity odor and melted glasses
no wonder it got Consumer Reports pick
for the best overall insect repellent
note that concentration matters they're
20 per keratin product topped the list
but at five percent it was one of the
worst performing products any toxicity
adverse effects when occurring primarily
manifested is eye irritation redness
vomiting and oral irritation but of
course you're not supposed to eat it or
spray it in your eyes but even
unintentional ingestion was associated
with only with relatively minor toxicity
what about the electronic mosquito
repellent gizmos 10 studies done in all
ten found that there was no difference
in the number of mosquitoes landing on
people with or without the gizmos and
experiments out in the field confirm no
effect on preventing mosquito bites
picardin was roughly based on a black
pepper compound but like DEET is a
synthetic chemical are there any natural
repellents of course just because
something is natural doesn't mean it's
necessarily safe strict nine is a
natural product of the strychnine tree
and ricin from Castor beans is 10 000
times deadlier still in fact the top 10
most toxic poisons are all natural but
let's look at the mosquito repellent
effects of about 20 essential oils
compared to a placebo control group and
to DEET the asterisks point to the
significant result so here's a cleaner
Peak as you can see only five had any
lasting effect at all peppermint and
lemongrass oil were effective for 30
minutes spearmint and garlic oil started
working but didn't even last that long
cinnamon oil though reduced mosquito
attraction for one and a half hours the
remaining essential oils had no
significant effect on mosquito
attraction at any time point and this
includes citronella a channel was the
most widely used repellent before DEET
was invented and it's still used today
in many formulations despite inferior
efficacy at lower concentrations it may
only last a few minutes and at higher
concentration citronella can cause skin
irritation
compared to a complete protection time
of six hours for DEET citronella may
only last 10 and a half minutes
therefore citronella may be acceptable
for brief exposure to nuisance
mosquitoes but it is not advised for
protection if you really can't afford to
get bit essential oils read this family
medicine Journal editorial have no
Effectiveness and are not recommended
but that was before we learned about
Lemon Eucalyptus the only plant-based
repellent recommended by the CDC those
should not be used by pregnant women or
children younger than three years of age
Consumer Reports listed it as one of
their top three picks warding off
mosquitoes and ticks for at least seven
hours all the other Botanical products
they tested failed but forty percent
Lemon Eucalyptus was shown to prevent
bites for four to seven hours after
application for aggressive species of
mosquitoes for greater than 12 hours for
less aggressive mosquitoes a period of
prevention greater than at least a 10
percent DEET repellent
[Music]
thank you